So, imagine you're standing on a street anywhere in America
إذاً، تخيل أنك تقف على شارع في أي مكان في أمريكا
and a Japanese man comes up to you and says,
ويأتي رجل ياباني إليك ويقول،
"Excuse me, what is the name of this block?"
" من فضلك، ما هو أسم هذه الجادة ؟"
And you say, "I'm sorry, well, this is Oak Street, that's Elm Street.
وتقول أنت، " أنا آسف. حسناً، هذا شارع أوك، وذلك شارع إلم.
This is 26th, that's 27th."
هذا رقم 26، وذلك رقم 27."
He says, "OK, but what is the name of that block?"
فيقول هو، " حسناً، جيد. ما هو أسم هذه الجادة ؟"
You say, "Well, blocks don't have names.
وتقول أنت، " حسناً، الجادة السكنية لا تحمل أسماء.
Streets have names; blocks are just the
للشوارع أسماء. الجادة السكنية هي مجرد
unnamed spaces in between streets."
الفضاء غير المسمى بين الشوارع."
He leaves, a little confused and disappointed.
ويغادر هو، مرتبك قليلاً ومحبط.
So, now imagine you're standing on a street, anywhere in Japan,
إذاً، الآن تخيل أنك تقف على شارع في أي مكان في اليابان،
you turn to a person next to you and say,
وتلتفت إلى الشخص القريب منك وتقول،
"Excuse me, what is the name of this street?"
" من فضلك، ما هو أسم هذا الشارع؟"
They say, "Oh, well that's Block 17 and this is Block 16."
فيرد، " أوه، حسناً هذه الجادة رقم 17 ووهذه الجادة رقم 16."
And you say, "OK, but what is the name of this street?"
وتقول أنت، " حسناً، ما هو أسم هذا الشارع؟"
And they say, "Well, streets don't have names.
فيرد، " حسناً، الشوارع لا تحمل أسماء.
Blocks have names.
للجادات السكنية أسماء
Just look at Google Maps here. There's Block 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.
فقط ألقي نظرة على خرائط غوغل هنا. فهناك الجادة رقم، 14، 15، 16، 17، 18،19.
All of these blocks have names,
لكل هذه الجادات السكنية أسماء.
and the streets are just the unnamed spaces in between the blocks.
الشوارع هي مجرد الفراغات بدون أسماء بين الجادات السكنية .
And you say then, "OK, then how do you know your home address?"
ثم تقول أنت، " حسناً، إذاً كيف ستعرف عنوان منزلك؟"
He said, "Well, easy, this is District Eight.
فيرد، " حسناً، سهلة، هذا هو الحيّ الثامن.
There's Block 17, house number one."
وهناك الجادة رقم 17، المنزل رقم واحد."
You say, "OK, but walking around the neighborhood,
فتقول أنت، " حسناً. لكن بالتجول في الجوار،
I noticed that the house numbers don't go in order."
لاحظت أن أرقام المنازل ليست بالترتيب."
He says, "Of course they do. They go in the order in which they were built.
فيرد، " بالطبع مرتبة. إنها بالترتيب الذي بُنيت به.
The first house ever built on a block is house number one.
أول منزل تم بناؤه في الجادة هو المنزل رقم واحد.
The second house ever built is house number two.
والمنزل الثاني الذي تم بناؤه هو المنزل رقم اثنين.
Third is house number three. It's easy. It's obvious."
والمنزل الثالث رقم ثلاثة. إنها سهلة. وواضحة."
So, I love that sometimes we need to
إذاً، فأنا أحب ذلك أننا بعض الأحيان نحتاج
go to the opposite side of the world
للذهاب إلى الجانب العكسي من العالم
to realize assumptions we didn't even know we had,
لإدراك الفرضيات التي لم نعرف حتى أنها لدينا،
and realize that the opposite of them may also be true.
وإدراك أن عكسها ربما يكون صحيحاً أيضاً.
So, for example, there are doctors in China
لذا، كمثال، هناك أطباء في الصين
who believe that it's their job to keep you healthy.
الذين يعتقدون أن عملهم هو الحفاظ عليك بصحة جيدة.
So, any month you are healthy you pay them,
لذا، ففي أي شهر تكون بصحة جيدة تقوم بالدفع لهم،
and when you're sick you don't have to pay them because they failed
وعندما تكون مريضاً لا ينبغي عليك الدفع لهم لأنهم فشلوا
at their job. They get rich when you're healthy, not sick.
في عملهم. إنهم يصبحون أغنياء عندما تكون بصحة جيدة، ليس مريضاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In most music, we think of the "one"
في معظم الموسيقى نعتقد أن " واحد"
as the downbeat, the beginning of the musical phrase: one, two, three, four.
هو بداية الإيقاع، للفقرة الموسيقية. واحد، اثنين ثلاثة اربعة.
But in West African music, the "one"
لكن عند موسيقى غرب أفريقيا "واحد"
is thought of as the end of the phrase,
يعتقد أنها نهاية الفقرة،
like the period at the end of a sentence.
مثل النقطة في نهاية الجملة.
So, you can hear it not just in the phrasing, but the way they count off their music:
لذا، يمكنك سماعها ليس فقط في الصياغ، لكن بالطريقة التي يعدون بها موسيقاهم.
two, three, four, one.
اثنين، ثلاثة، أربعة، واحد.
And this map is also accurate.
وهذه الخريطة كذلك دقيقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There's a saying that whatever true thing you can say about India,
هناك مقولة أن أي شئ يمكنك قوله عن الهند،
the opposite is also true.
فان عكسه كذلك صحيح.
So, let's never forget, whether at TED, or anywhere else,
لذا، دعونا لا ننسى، سواء في تيد، أو أي مكان آخر،
that whatever brilliant ideas you have or hear,
أنه أي فكرة ممتازة لديك أو تسمعها،
that the opposite may also be true.
فان العكس ربما يكون أيضاً صحيحاً.
Domo arigato gozaimashita.
Domo arigato gozaimashita.